So, how are we going to do the direction
prediction? We're going to have a table
that we will call a branch history table
or BHT. We will take the PC of the
instruction, grab the least significant
bits, and that's what we index into this
table with. So, it's the same as when
indexing into the BTB, but the entry
here is much smaller. The simplest
predictor will simply have a one bit
here that tells us if this is a not a
taken branch, meaning it's a non branch
or a not taken branch or when it's one,
it says that this is a taken branch. If
we get a zero from here, we just
increment the PC. If we get a one, we
use the BTB to tell us where to go. Just
like we were updating the BTB, we can
update this once we resolve the branch.
If we resolve to a taken branch, then we
put a one here and we write the
destination address into the BTB. If we
get a zero, if we decide that the branch
is not taken or that the instruction is
not a branch, then we put a zero here
and we don't update the BTB so that we
can use the BTB only for target
addresses that we really really need the
BTB for because an entry here can be
only a single bit. This table can be
quite large. So we can have lots of
instructions have entries here avoiding
conflicts between instructions that
commonly execute while still reserving
the small BTB which has much fewer
entries only for branches in that code.